<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two discourses the first, shewing how the chief criterions of philosophical truth, invented by speculative men, more eminently serve divine revelation, than either philosophy or natural religion. The second, manifesting how all the foundations of the intellectual world, viz. reason, morality, civil government, and religion, have been undermin'd by popish doctrine and policies. By Tho. Mannyngham, M.A fellow of New Colledge in Oxford, and Rector of East-Tysted in Hant-Shire.</title>
            <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216239</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827979</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1854:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two discourses the first, shewing how the chief criterions of philosophical truth, invented by speculative men, more eminently serve divine revelation, than either philosophy or natural religion. The second, manifesting how all the foundations of the intellectual world, viz. reason, morality, civil government, and religion, have been undermin'd by popish doctrine and policies. By Tho. Mannyngham, M.A fellow of New Colledge in Oxford, and Rector of East-Tysted in Hant-Shire.</title>
                  <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 172, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Will. Cademan, at the Popes Head in the lower Walk of the New Exchange in the Strand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves. Though they appear to be part of the final gathering, the verso of the second mentions this work.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Philosophy and religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO DISCOURSES: THE <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſhewing how the <hi>Chief Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terions</hi> of Philoſophical <hi>Truth,</hi> invented by <hi>Speculative</hi> men, more <hi>Eminently</hi> ſerve <hi>Divine</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, than either <hi>Philoſophy</hi> or <hi>Natural Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Second,</hi> manifeſting how all the <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the <hi>Intellectual World, viz. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Morality, Civil Government,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> have been undermin'd by <hi>Popiſh Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Policies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Mannyngham,</hi> M. A Fellow of <hi>New Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Eaſt-Tyſted</hi> in <hi>Hant-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Cademan,</hi> at the <hi>Popes</hi> Head in the lower Walk of the New Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:3"/>
            <head>To my very Worthy and Ingenious Friend, Mr. <hi>Thomas Palmer,</hi> one of the Honourable Members of the <hi>laſt,</hi> and of this <hi>preſent</hi> Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> beg leave for theſe <hi>Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to appear under the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> and <hi>Friendſhip</hi> of your <hi>Name,</hi> as containing in
<pb facs="tcp:32405:4"/>them ſome <hi>general Remarks</hi> and <hi>Hints</hi> in <hi>Learning,</hi> which I ſuppoſe, may not be altogether unſuitable to your <hi>Genius,</hi> to your natural Inclination for <hi>varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>Thought</hi> with ſome <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency</hi> of <hi>Epreſſion.</hi> The <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part</hi> of what I now preſent you, was the effort of my <hi>younger Years,</hi> and therefore may appear to ſome to contain more of the <hi>warmth</hi> of <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination,</hi> than of the <hi>cooler ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:32405:4"/>of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> to diſcover rather a <hi>wild Range</hi> in <hi>Learning,</hi> an <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Revelling</hi> in <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> than any mature Reſearch into <hi>Principles,</hi> and the <hi>Cognizances</hi> of <hi>Truth;</hi> any <hi>compleat Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and <hi>Final Triumph</hi> over <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</hi> But let the <hi>Opinions</hi> of Men be what they pleaſe, I hope they will not deter you from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troniſing the <hi>ſucceſs:</hi> Though in relation to <hi>this former Diſcourſe,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:32405:5"/>I may without much Vanity pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you <hi>ſome ſecurity,</hi> ſince it has been already <hi>approved</hi> by much better <hi>Judges,</hi> than per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps are left to <hi>condemn</hi> it. I am now Sir retiring from the World, and that which always was its brighteſt Scene to me, your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful <hi>Converſation;</hi> and am therefore willing to leave you, and perhaps a few more of my Friends, ſome little <hi>Image,</hi> ſome faint <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> of me, in the <hi>Eſſays</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:32405:5"/>of my younger Studies. I muſt confeſs, I have now another <hi>Taſt</hi> of things than what I formerly had, partly my experience in the World, and partly the <hi>new Ferment</hi> of <hi>Humors</hi> in our Nation, having taken from me all the <hi>Remains</hi> of an <hi>Innocent Ambition.</hi> By the <hi>providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>free unconditionate generoſity</hi> of that <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, Sir <hi>John Norton,</hi> I am comfortably placed in an <hi>agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:32405:6"/>ſtation</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> and am now paſſionately deſirous to collect my ſelf, to be <hi>known</hi> to <hi>few,</hi> to be <hi>envy'd</hi> by <hi>none:</hi> If ever I had any <hi>eſteem</hi> among <hi>ſome,</hi> either through <hi>chance</hi> or the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> of <hi>Friends,</hi> I ſhould now be glad to have my <hi>Name</hi> as <hi>Friendly neglected,</hi> as it was firſt <hi>raiſed;</hi> for I always accounted a <hi>great Reputation,</hi> and a <hi>great Infamy</hi> to be <hi>equal Afflictions;</hi> and the <hi>unknown
<pb facs="tcp:32405:6"/>untalk'd</hi> of Man to be only <hi>Bleſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet though I am entring into the ſolid Peace and Contentment of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate life</hi> I leave you, Sir, engaged in the higheſt Sphere of <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Action;</hi> but I leave you under a deep ſence of the Intereſt and obligation of the <hi>beſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> in the World; a <hi>Religion,</hi> out of which no <hi>good</hi> and <hi>wiſe</hi> Subject of this Nation can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous
<pb facs="tcp:32405:7"/>to <hi>live,</hi> and <hi>in which</hi> even <hi>Repenting Atheiſts</hi> chooſe to <hi>Dye!</hi> I leave you alſo guarded with the <hi>Hereditary</hi> and <hi>choſen</hi> Principles of <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> with all the <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Acquired</hi> Bleſſings of <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Improvement;</hi> eſpecially, with that Law <hi>of Kindneſs</hi> in your <hi>Soul,</hi> legible even in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward characters of your <hi>Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> which will hardly ever ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to <hi>Err much,</hi> either in a
<pb facs="tcp:32405:7"/>
               <hi>Publick</hi> or a <hi>Private</hi> Life; it being very difficult for a perſon of <hi>large Affections,</hi> of great <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty</hi> in <hi>Converſation,</hi> of ſharp and quick <hi>Reflections</hi> in <hi>ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> thought, ever to become <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> in <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Habitually looſe</hi> in <hi>private Manners.</hi> And O! that ſuch an <hi>amicable ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>Diſpoſition,</hi> as gently reigns through all your <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>deſigns,</hi> were every where mingled with the <hi>Policy</hi> of our
<pb facs="tcp:32405:8"/>
               <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and that the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of our <hi>great Aſſembly</hi> were every where <hi>temper'd</hi> with ſuch an <hi>Healing Meekneſs!</hi> then <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> might distil like Balm upon our <hi>Nation,</hi> then might we ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily recover our <hi>Secular Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to the Admiration and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> of our <hi>Forreign Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers:</hi> then might we <hi>ſtrike down</hi> our <hi>Errors</hi> in <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as the <hi>Prieſts</hi> did hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:32405:8"/>the <hi>Sacrifices</hi> at the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> not with the <hi>Haſt</hi> and <hi>Fury</hi> of Anger and Revenge, but with that <hi>deliberate ſtrength,</hi> that <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn delay,</hi> which proceeded wholly from a <hi>Conviction</hi> and <hi>Senſe</hi> of <hi>Duty,</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> then might our <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern by <hi>Love,</hi> our <hi>Religion</hi> by <hi>Charity,</hi> and all our <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> unite into the <hi>Everlaſting ſecurities</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:32405:9"/>which is the <hi>hearty Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of him who deſires to be known by no greater Title than that of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Faithful and moſt Obedient Friend and Servant,</hi> Tho. Mannnygham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32405:9"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning TRUTH.</head>
            <p>HE who has had the Curioſity to obſerve our <hi>Modern Scepticiſm,</hi> and been any thing acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thoſe looſer Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32405:10"/>which almoſt univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally occur; (wherein reſtleſs Conſciences have endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all the little Arts of ſpecious Sophiſtry, to work out to themſelves a <hi>Stupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> rather than a <hi>Quiet,</hi> a <hi>Charm</hi> than a <hi>Satisfaction</hi>) may readily reflect how <hi>Natural Theology</hi> erected chiefly on <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> (the great <hi>Diana</hi> of this <hi>Mechanick</hi> age) is now become the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of all thoſe who pretend to eſtabliſh their irreligion by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32405:10"/>
               <hi>Argument</hi> and <hi>Syllogiſm.</hi> For downright poſitive <hi>Atheiſm</hi> has found but very few ſerious and declared Abettors; has ſometimes ſprung from the fumes and madneſs of <hi>Wine,</hi> and <hi>Luſt;</hi> has been the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper of an Hour, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox or Rant of <hi>heated Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> not an <hi>Opinion,</hi> or a <hi>morning thought;</hi> and for the moſt part, has been rather <hi>ſworn</hi> up, than <hi>aſſerted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtianity had that <hi>Serpent Philoſophy</hi> to deal
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32405:11"/>with in its very Cradle, and through all its ſtrength of Centuries has received its fierceſt aſſaults from that <hi>Monster.</hi> By <hi>vain Philoſophy,</hi> ſo rigorouſly condemned in the <hi>Epistles;</hi> the Learned generally underſtand the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick Theology</hi> compoſed for the moſt part of <hi>Pythagorean Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples;</hi> and that the <hi>Epicurean</hi> and <hi>Stoical</hi> Sects were as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious as any in the Apoſtles times, the Diſputes of St. <hi>Paul</hi> recordedin <hi>Acts</hi> 17. v. 18. ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32405:11"/>inform us. Not long after this, that <hi>Man</hi> whom <hi>Origen</hi> ſo rationally and ſo perſpicuouſly anſwered, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd againſt the <hi>whole Bible</hi> with all the Artillery of inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Eloquence, and falſe reaſonings, deduced from a commixture of <hi>Barbarian</hi> and <hi>Grecian</hi> Placits. Then <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Julian,</hi> &amp;c. but particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly their Anceſtor <hi>Porphyry</hi> (whom ſome of the Fathers counted it Religion to Curſe) ſought by all the darkeſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32405:12"/>methods of Hell to leſſen and deſtroy the Authority of the <hi>Holy Bible:</hi> For accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that imperfect ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which we find of thoſe fifteen Books he wrote againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> he is recorded there to have jeered at <hi>it</hi> for a mean ſimplicity of <hi>Style,</hi> and for innumerable <hi>repugnancies;</hi> to have attributed its <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> to ſecret Combinations of Writers after the <hi>Fact,</hi> or <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated</hi> them to other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Circumſtances; and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32405:12"/>to have aſcribed all its <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> to the force of <hi>Egyptian Magick,</hi> and the operation of Devils. Now all this was contrived in honour and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the <hi>Platonic Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> ſo highly reverenced by the <hi>Sacred Order</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrian</hi> School. Yet all theſe men have ſpent their utmoſt Venom, done their worſt, and the <hi>gates of Hell</hi> have not prevailed.</p>
            <p>For another ſucceſſion of Goſpel Adverſaries, we may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32405:13"/>with Candor enough reckon <hi>Aquinas</hi> and the <hi>School-men,</hi> who have moſt deplorably undermined the <hi>Scriptures</hi> with the Principles of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and although <hi>accidentally,</hi> yet they have been as really pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as any we have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to named. Their <hi>intentions</hi> were doubtleſs <hi>innocent,</hi> but we can never ſufficiently la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their intolerable <hi>Leiſure,</hi> which occaſioned them for want of better imploy, to ſpin out all the ſtrength of <hi>Divine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32405:13"/>Writings</hi> into nice and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable <hi>Volumns.</hi> Whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the advices of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may ſeem to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who have ſpent ſo much time in thoſe <hi>Studies</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, that they are bound for their <hi>Reputation-ſake,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them to others; who tell us, <hi>thoſe</hi> alone will make a man <hi>cloſe</hi> and <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative,</hi> quick and ſagacious in diſcovering the <hi>Point</hi> and <hi>Knot</hi> of the <hi>Controverſie,</hi> which perhaps was ty'd only for the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32405:14"/>
               <hi>Trick-ſake;</hi> who would have us lie ſeven or eight years in a <hi>dark room,</hi> that when we come abroad into the <hi>open day,</hi> we may <hi>think</hi> we ſee <hi>clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> who though they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have miſerably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented the <hi>Couſenage,</hi> yet ſtill cry up and maintain the <hi>prodigy,</hi> and to prevent a <hi>ſawcy precociouſneſs</hi> in Learning, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite others to drudge in <hi>their methods,</hi> to be vigilant and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive on <hi>ſubtile Entities,</hi> till they become like thoſe deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32405:14"/>ſort of <hi>Contemplators,</hi> who never fix their eyes more <hi>ſteadfastly</hi> than when they <hi>ſee nothing:</hi> notwithſtanding, I ſay, all theſe large promiſes and encouragements for the reading of the Schoolmen, there are altogether as obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant perſons, who will not ſtick to affirm, that 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently owing to that <hi>Load</hi> and <hi>Corruption</hi> of our <hi>Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> that men are generally grown ſo looſe and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous in their <hi>Reaſonings,</hi> that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32405:15"/>with little pains or art they can prove <hi>any thing,</hi> or <hi>nothing;</hi> and that moſt of thoſe <hi>Religious Wars</hi> which at this day infeſt <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> are chiefly owing to that fatal invention of <hi>School-Divinity,</hi> that <hi>Gun-powder</hi> of <hi>Learning.</hi> All this would be moſt amazingly dreadful, but that there is ſomewhat worſe to come.</p>
            <p>There is ſtill <hi>another Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> behind, and that has o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened another <hi>Gate</hi> in <hi>Hell,</hi> and ſent forth a piece of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32405:15"/>
               <hi>blackeſt Sophiſtry</hi> that the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Synod</hi> can dictate. Its reputed Author, <hi>Benedictus</hi> de <hi>Spinoza; one</hi> who has run through a whole <hi>Amsterdam</hi> of <hi>Religions</hi> himſelf, and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that <hi>Athens</hi> of promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Worſhip</hi> with one more of his own Invention. Where he has given them all the difficulties of <hi>Scripture-Hiſtory</hi> and <hi>Chronology</hi> amaſs'd and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanſed; all the Doubts and Controverſies of <hi>Commentators</hi> poſitively <hi>determined</hi> on the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32405:16"/>worſt ſide; a <hi>Rapſodie</hi> of Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions from <hi>Talmud</hi> and <hi>Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran;</hi> and a Feature of <hi>Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> borrowed from every <hi>Hereſie, Schiſm,</hi> and <hi>Sect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the Bible to be <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> but with this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo, that the Philoſophers <hi>Reaſon</hi> is ſtill a more <hi>infallible word</hi> of God; that its <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies</hi> were accommodated to <hi>Prejudice, Fancy,</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;</hi> Its <hi>Miracles</hi> the <hi>Wonders</hi> of the Ignorant; its whole end
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32405:16"/>and ſcope <hi>Political,</hi> for the better ſecurity of <hi>Government;</hi> and its <hi>popular Doctrine</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended only for the <hi>Herd</hi> to ſquare their groſs <hi>Obedience</hi> by: and all this, becauſe there occur ſome <hi>Expreſſions</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> altogether unworthy (as he imagines) of thoſe clear and evident diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of <hi>Nature</hi> lately found out and <hi>Demonſtrated</hi> by the <hi>Divine Carteſius;</hi> whom he never mentions but with the greateſt veneration imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32405:17"/>with all the Eulogies that the moſt raviſhed inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can ſuggeſt; whereas if at any time he <hi>confeſſes Chriſt,</hi> 'tis like the <hi>Devil</hi> in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, with <hi>Horror</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctance,</hi> and (like him too) he ſeems firſt <hi>Tormented</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Exiſtence</hi> of a Deity againſt the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> and the certainty of the <hi>Bibles Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> againſt the <hi>Anti-ſcripturiſt,</hi> have been in all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ages, but eſpecially of late, ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirmed and eſtabliſhed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32405:17"/>both from <hi>Pulpit</hi> and <hi>Preſs,</hi> through all the poſſibility of <hi>Reaſoning,</hi> all the Amplitude of <hi>Topics,</hi> whether <hi>Theological, Metaphyſical, Phyſical, Moral,</hi> or <hi>Mathematical,</hi> that were they handſomely collected and ſumm'd up, they would without Controverſie make a <hi>Compendium</hi> of the <hi>propereſt Logick</hi> yet extant; and yet this <hi>Infamous</hi> Book preſents our <hi>Reaſoning</hi> Men with a farther ſcruple ſtill, where freely granting the <hi>Revelation</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:32405:18"/>of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> it notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding concludes, that the holy Bible is only a <hi>popular Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem</hi> of <hi>Pious Political Errors; Regnum Devotionis, non Verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> Wherefore I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour at preſent only to make good this <hi>one Propoſition,</hi> viz. <hi>That the chief Criterions or Canons of Philoſophical Truth, which have been invented and allowed by ſpeculative Men, are much more abundantly convincing when applied to matters of Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:32405:18"/>
            <p>Now <hi>Philoſophical Truth</hi> is capable of being conſidered but theſe <hi>two ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. In reſpect of its <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> or <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> account.</item>
               <item>II. In reſpect of its <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation</hi> to our <hi>Natural Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. In reſpect of its <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> or <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> account.</p>
            <p>And here we have ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32405:19"/>late <hi>Authors</hi> very laborious in <hi>Tranſcriptions,</hi> who have not ſcrupled to make <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy co-incident</hi> with <hi>Revelation</hi> it ſelf, deriving it in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued <hi>Tradition</hi> from the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> and thereby concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it no other than the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> of a <hi>primary Revelation.</hi> They make the buſineſs very ſhort, telling us, that doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Adam</hi> was created with a <hi>perfect knowledge</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and that from him this Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was tranſmitted by <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32405:19"/>to <hi>Noah,</hi> from <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons and Nephews to the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> from them to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> from the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> to the <hi>Phenicians,</hi> from <hi>Phenicia</hi> it ſailed into <hi>Greece,</hi> ſo to the <hi>Latins,</hi> and from thence 'twas propagated to theſe ſeptentrional parts, where we have the <hi>Genealogy</hi> of Philoſophy as clearly and ſuccinctly delineated, as that of our <hi>King,</hi> from <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we cannot ſuppoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32405:20"/>that <hi>Adam</hi> tranſmitted that Knowledg of Nature, which he enjoyed during the <hi>ſtate</hi> of his <hi>Innocency,</hi> and which he received either from <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Infuſion,</hi> or <hi>connate Idea</hi>'s of things: Nay if he had, he would have given his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity a <hi>falſe Philoſophy,</hi> ſince that <hi>whole Nature</hi> was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards forced to follow the <hi>Law</hi> of its <hi>Curſe,</hi> ſince <hi>Thorns</hi> and <hi>Bryars</hi> were not in the Scheme of Vegetables, and the <hi>Serpent</hi> was to be new ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32405:20"/>again. But if he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us the Knowledge he had gathered from much <hi>Experience,</hi> and a <hi>long Life</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his <hi>Fall,</hi> when perhaps his Faculties were not <hi>very much perfecter</hi> than ours, and ſtood in as great want of a <hi>Logick</hi> for their better information, I do not ſee any great benefit we could receive from ſuch a <hi>Tradition;</hi> and all that the Aſſerters of this Opinion can make good will be only this, that we have received one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32405:21"/>more <hi>Curſe</hi> from him than we thought of, and that he has propagated to his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>Sin, Death,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who were a mighty and ruling <hi>Nation,</hi> when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were but one choſen <hi>Family,</hi> ſhould receive all their Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Learning from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, which as yet had not ſo much as any <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Canon,</hi> any Law to walk by, but what it received ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the continual <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32405:21"/>of <hi>Angels,</hi> or ſomewhat elſe both <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable</hi> to the Poſterity of <hi>Cham,</hi> is more than our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Hiſtorical probability will allow us to affirm. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it leſs abſurd to make <hi>Joſeph</hi> the great Interpreter of Dreams, the ſame with <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus,</hi> and to be their renowned <hi>Law-giver,</hi> when as before his arrival thither, they lived in all pomp and <hi>Trading, Municipal Laws,</hi> and confluence of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:32405:22"/>nay, and he himſelf was but a part of the <hi>Iſhmae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites Traffick,</hi> Gen. 37.36.</p>
            <p>The firſt riſe and exerciſe of the <hi>Heathen Theology</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted only in ſome <hi>Myſtical Rites,</hi> afterwards recited in <hi>Hymns</hi> and <hi>Muſical Odes;</hi> and ſeeing the acknowledgment of a God is allowed to be <hi>Univerſal,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural;</hi> why might not theſe <hi>Barbarous efforts</hi> in Religion wholly ſpring from the <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Notion</hi> of a Deity <hi>naturally
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32405:22"/>inherent,</hi> without any <hi>particular</hi> derivation from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church? The <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> do indeed aſcribe ſome advantages to the <hi>Phenitians,</hi> which <hi>Tacitus</hi> particularly mentions, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Art of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation,</hi> and a <hi>few Letters;</hi> but that they held a general <hi>Mart of Learning,</hi> and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted <hi>Colonies of humane Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> into <hi>Greece, Africa, Spain,</hi> and the chief parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> which border on the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> is certainly no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32405:23"/>other than one of Mr. <hi>Bochar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi>'s Learned Whimſies. We uſually eſteem our <hi>Trading Towns</hi> as Brutiſh a part of Mankind as any of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, where <hi>Gain</hi> and <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs</hi> ſeldom allow any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals for <hi>Meditation,</hi> any Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for <hi>deep thought;</hi> and we may eaſily believe the <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Phenicians</hi> to have had no better <hi>ſpeculations</hi> than that of their <hi>Cynoſura</hi> for the ſafer Conduct of a <hi>Cock-boat;</hi> no other <hi>Society-Invention</hi> than that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32405:23"/>of a <hi>Royal die,</hi> which came neither from a <hi>Jewiſh Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> nor an <hi>Egyptian Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick,</hi> but (as good Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans inform us) was happily hinted by the <hi>experimental</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy of a Dog.</p>
            <p>But grant theſe Eaſtern Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to have excelled in ſome uſeful parts of the <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> yet we may give a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> account of the riſe of thoſe without having any recourſe to the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> ſince they may be probably ſuppoſed to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32405:24"/>have taken their Origin either from <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> or a <hi>commodious Situation,</hi> or <hi>both;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Egyptians Geometry</hi> might be owing to the inundations of <hi>Nile,</hi> which cauſed them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to Survey their confuſion of Lands; the <hi>Serenity</hi> of the <hi>Air,</hi> and an undiſturbed Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon might invite the <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to look up, and by long obſervation underſtand the courſe of ſome few <hi>Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and the compulſion of the <hi>Phenicians</hi> or <hi>Canaanites</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32405:24"/>the Coaſts of the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> by the Sword of <hi>Joſhua</hi> might force them to ſeek mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on the Ocean, and drive them to the little Arts of <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Navigation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> whoſe <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Travels</hi> have adminiſtred much to this Fancy, is recorded by <hi>Porphyry</hi> to have brought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the <hi>Hebrews</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Dreams, or of their Interpretation, which yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them was never count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32405:25"/>an <hi>Art,</hi> but an <hi>Inſpiration.</hi> If the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſuch diffuſers of <hi>ſecular Learning,</hi> why are the <hi>wiſest Men</hi> of their own Nation (ſuch as <hi>Joſeph, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi>) cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractered and deciphered to us in the Bible, with a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon ſo advantagious to the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>other Nations;</hi> as that they were skilled in all the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> that their Wiſdom excelled all the Wiſdom of the <hi>Eaſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi> and of <hi>Babilon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:32405:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Schools</hi> and <hi>Colledges</hi> we are taught they had, though not ſuch as ſome of our <hi>European Seminaries</hi> for <hi>frivolous</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtical Education;</hi> but for the weighty inſtruction of the <hi>Sons</hi> of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> for the reading and interpreting of their <hi>Sacred Law.</hi> Grant that ſome of the more <hi>Mystical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical</hi> parts of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorizing Philoſophy,</hi> or ſome of thoſe <hi>Fables</hi> which the Poets borrowed from the <hi>Corruption</hi> of Tradition, were
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32405:26"/>derived thence; muſt it needs follow that all the <hi>unmix'd</hi> and <hi>Argumentizing</hi> Philoſophy, all <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> (the effects of <hi>Curioſity</hi> and <hi>accidental</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergency) muſt be brought from <hi>Canaan?</hi> If <hi>Plato</hi> at any time writes that he received a blind Notion <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, muſt they be preſently no other than the hateful, and therefore <hi>concealed Hebrews,</hi> when as all the World beſides was eſteemed <hi>Barbarian</hi> to him.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:32405:26"/>
            <p>Now the great maintainers of this <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> whether <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> and <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> or more modern Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaries, ſeem to have bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed the hint chiefly from the eloquent <hi>Jew Joſephus,</hi> who in his Treatiſe againſt <hi>Appion</hi> the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Grammarian endeavours to prove together with the <hi>Antiquity</hi> the <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Learning</hi> alſo of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Yet out of an <hi>Hereditary</hi> preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, and a notorious <hi>National</hi> Pride, he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32405:27"/>may be thought to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the modeſty of ſober Argument on that ſubject, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially being ſo highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by the <hi>jeers</hi> of <hi>Appion,</hi> who undertakes to prove them originally <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and that they were turned out thence with their <hi>Heliopolitan Moſes,</hi> for an <hi>infamous Diſeaſe.</hi> With theſe moſt defamatory ſpeeches <hi>Blaſpheming</hi> his Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as his own words ſignify; this (I ſay) might exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him to an haughty dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32405:27"/>of all the <hi>Learning</hi> of the whole World beſides, and to make their pompous and long celebrated <hi>Wiſdom</hi> appear no other than ſome <hi>broken Light,</hi> ſome <hi>imperfect fragments</hi> deriv'd from them.</p>
            <p>However ſince by the very confeſſion of thoſe, who would make out ſuch a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, it is now mixed and fermented with the vain <hi>additions</hi> and <hi>falſities</hi> of the ignorant Gentiles, as it appears but a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32405:28"/>full of Horror and the miſguidings of the Night, we cannot upon the account of <hi>Tradition</hi> or <hi>Revelation,</hi> be faithfully aſſured of any <hi>Truth,</hi> any <hi>Certainty</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>Now there are none of theſe imputations, which can be charg'd on the <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> eſpecially on that <hi>neceſſary</hi> part, on which our <hi>Belief,</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> and our <hi>Salvation</hi> depends There's no <hi>obſcurity,</hi> unleſs that which may ariſe from <hi>too great a Luſtre;</hi> no dark Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32405:28"/>from <hi>Delphos,</hi> whoſe <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation</hi> ſtill required <hi>another Oracle;</hi> but all its Doctrine is like <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Light,</hi> nothing more <hi>Familiar</hi> and Domeſtick, and yet <hi>Myſterious</hi> too. What if the <hi>Revelations</hi> of St. <hi>John</hi> are ſtill in ſome parts <hi>vailed,</hi> are the <hi>ſhadows</hi> in our Heavenly Landſcape, yet we doubt not but the <hi>Ages to come</hi> will ſee them perfectly fulfilled into their true <hi>Shine</hi> and <hi>Perſpicuity;</hi> and what we cannot here at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to will but make our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32405:29"/>
               <hi>Scene</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> larger. Neither are the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any vain <hi>Additions;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> cannot faſten their <hi>Talmud,</hi> nor the <hi>Papiſts</hi> their <hi>Traditions;</hi> ſuch are but <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s <hi>Miracles,</hi> and can never imitate the <hi>fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Neither could all the Armies, Emperors, or Perſecutions, all the Policy &amp; Malice of <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy <hi>one Article,</hi> blot out one <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Truth,</hi> but that ſame God, who firſt inſpired them, has
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32405:29"/>hitherto preſerved them, and we may with all devout con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence expect, that his never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlumbring <hi>Providence</hi> will be their <hi>Eternal Maſſorah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having done with the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storical</hi> account let us <hi>Secondly</hi> conſider <hi>Philoſophical Truth</hi> in an accommodation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to our <hi>Natural Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">I. To our <hi>Sences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe <hi>Teſtimony</hi> being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by a <hi>ſuperintendent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:32405:30"/>is the moſt infallible cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty we can naturally have of <hi>ſenſible</hi> things: which (as to its <hi>Mode</hi> of <hi>Derivation</hi>) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it proceeds from <hi>real Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> inherent in the Objects, or <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Phantaſms</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed on the Nerves and Brain, it matters not, ſince moſt men are ſufficiently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree'd in their <hi>Repreſentations,</hi> or <hi>Relative</hi> Truth, our Organs and Objects being rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed and circumſtantiated. Neither is it to any purpoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32405:30"/>for any one to obtrude upon us the frequent illuſions of <hi>Sight,</hi> ſince thoſe very <hi>Fallacies</hi> (as they call them) conſtitute an <hi>Art,</hi> and are the grand <hi>Maxims</hi> of our <hi>Opticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now although ſome have ſo deeply plunged into that degeneracy of <hi>Scepticiſm</hi> as to extract a Controverſie from every Particle of the Univerſe, and make their own exiſtence a Problem, yet has this been pointed at by the ſober part of Mankind, as the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32405:31"/>of Folly and forlorn Sot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſs. The very <hi>Pyrrhonians</hi> were not guilty of this Exceſs, who never deny their aſſent to the Paſſions, and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Senſe, but doubted whether the <hi>Natures</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Verities of things were from thence, or by any other way ſufficiently and infallibly known; which is convincing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt from their grand probability <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bears no relation to the immediate
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32405:31"/>
               <hi>appearances</hi> of Sence, but is wholly concerned in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, Syllogiſm, and the Conſequences of Science; and if at any time they did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, indulge themſelves a ſportive Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs about the familiar Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Sence, 'twas not ſo much to affront Truth, as to <hi>perſecute</hi> the <hi>haughty Dogmatist,</hi> and torture his ſurly poſitions; ſo that thoſe few <hi>abſurdities</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of their great Maſter <hi>Pyrrho</hi> can be nothing but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32405:32"/>
               <hi>Fiction</hi> and <hi>Comedy:</hi> as that he disbelieved all his Senſes, grew ſo callous and mortified with ſtupidity, as that he had taught his very Nerves and Fibres to deny themſelves; ſo dead drunk with <hi>Apathy,</hi> as to lye in a Carts way, and at another time moſt unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to doubt whether his Friend was in the Ditch or no. Theſe (I ſay) and ſuch like extravagant Relations, which occur in his Life, can be no other than the <hi>Burleſque</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:32405:32"/>of his <hi>Opinion;</hi> like that of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picurus</hi>'s, which from the pure abſtracted Contemplations on Nature, joyned with the moſt innocent delight of a Garden was by the viler <hi>Herd</hi> of that <hi>Sect</hi> corrupted into all groſs <hi>Senſuality,</hi> and the debauches of a City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> affirms of <hi>Pyrrho,</hi> that his <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a noble <hi>Generoſity</hi> of mind, and that in order for an undiſturbed tranquility of Life he introduced a <hi>polite
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32405:33"/>Genteel Mode</hi> of <hi>Philoſophizing</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And if ſo, ſuch a <hi>Scepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm</hi> as this would be the beſt breeding a Scholar could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, 'twould redeem the Learned from that <hi>ſnarle</hi> of <hi>Education,</hi> which many have moſt unhappily contracted from their little Victories in Scholaſtick Contentions, whence they become angry and ſick at every ſuſpence of Judgment in another, ſo ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32405:33"/>impatient of contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Argument, that they vilify and defame all <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature,</hi> becauſe the Age <hi>rebels</hi> againſt their Opinion. Whereas on the contrary the modeſt way of humbly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing our probabilities, and allowing the ſame freedom to others, would render <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> ſweet and eaſie, all conferences pleaſant, and be a great inſtrument of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing true <hi>Friendſhip</hi> in the World. He that grows hot
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32405:34"/>and turbid, that elbows in all his <hi>Philoſophick Diſputes,</hi> muſt needs be very proud of his own <hi>Sufficiencies,</hi> or very ignorant of the <hi>vanity</hi> of the Science he ſtickles for; and commonly the <hi>intemperate</hi> value of a <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation</hi> proceeds from the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of the Man; for he that is paſſionate for a <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Syſtem</hi> now, without doubt was ſo here-to fore for his <hi>Nuts,</hi> and is in all likelihood of ſtill following his Temper, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing warm and obſtinate in all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32405:34"/>the <hi>trivial</hi> concerns of <hi>Humane Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither would this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous method only give us ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier ſeaſons, and ſofter mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Converſe,</hi> but alſo a freer range to <hi>Fancy,</hi> and a loſs to <hi>new thought;</hi> ſince in matters <hi>wholly Philoſophical</hi> (where <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> are not concerned) <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm</hi> and <hi>Paradox</hi> may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Controverſie be eſteemed the <hi>pureſt Vehicles</hi> of Noble <hi>Wit,</hi> and unattempted <hi>Senſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:32405:35"/>
            <p>It need not ſtartle us that the <hi>Roman</hi> Writers do often inſinuate a very contemptible regard for the <hi>Senſes,</hi> ſince all that, is in order for the better colouring the <hi>contradictions</hi> of their <hi>Maſs.</hi> Hence a late <hi>French</hi> Author in his <hi>Reſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> after <hi>Truth,</hi> having preſented his Reader with a long tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous repetition of the <hi>invincible Illuſions</hi> of the <hi>Senſes</hi> (ſuch as a <hi>ſtick</hi> half in the <hi>Water,</hi> and a <hi>ſquare</hi> Tower at a <hi>diſtance</hi>) moſt triumphantly concludes,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32405:35"/>that they were given to Men, as they are to Brutes, only for the <hi>preſervation</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> not as the <hi>Ports</hi> of <hi>Merchandiſe</hi> and <hi>Science,</hi> but of <hi>Defence</hi> and <hi>Safety.</hi> As if our <hi>ſight</hi> ſerv'd us only for the conduct of our ſteps, or for ſecuring us from a <hi>Precipice,</hi> whereas that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt unlimited <hi>Senſe</hi> extends it's <hi>Royalty</hi> through the whole <hi>Univerſe,</hi> purvey's for all the <hi>capacity</hi> of the <hi>Intellect,</hi> and points at what it cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <hi>diſcover.</hi> For by the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32405:36"/>things</hi> of the <hi>Creation,</hi> the great <hi>Inviſibles</hi> are <hi>Collected.</hi> But we need not labour any longer in this point, ſince <hi>thoſe perſons,</hi> againſt whom our Diſcourſe is chiefly directed, are ſo vigorous for the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of <hi>Senſe,</hi> that they ſcarce allow any other, but make the moſt ſublimated <hi>Knowledge</hi> a <hi>Tumult</hi> of <hi>Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſms;</hi> all <hi>Thought, Local Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> all <hi>Reaſon, Mechaniſm;</hi> and the whole <hi>Encyclopede</hi> of <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> but a <hi>brisker Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:32405:36"/>of the <hi>Blood.</hi> How ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous ſoever this Opinion is, yet it ſufficiently ſerves our purpoſe, as it eſtabliſhes <hi>Senſe</hi> to be an undoubted <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terion</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> as far as we contend, or within its proper <hi>Sphere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now ſee the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant concern of this <hi>Crite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion</hi> in matters of <hi>Revelation,</hi> which will preſently appear, if we conſider, that this was the <hi>firſt</hi> and is the <hi>laſt Evidence,</hi> of <hi>Divine Miracles,</hi> on which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32405:37"/>all <hi>revealed Religion</hi> is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and that <hi>Tradition</hi> it ſelf makes no Argument until 'tis ultimately reſolved into the <hi>certainty</hi> of the <hi>Senſes. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> made their conſtant appeal to <hi>them.</hi> What we have <hi>ſeen,</hi> and what we have <hi>heard</hi> was ſtill the <hi>Apoſtles Logick,</hi> and an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to <hi>Miracles,</hi> was the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> How ſolicitous was our Saviour after his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> to give the ſenſes their full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32405:37"/>This made him condeſcend to heal St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi>'s Infidelity with a touch, which immediately ſhed a ſtrong Conviction through his Soul, that ſtraight way broke forth into a glorious acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legment, <hi>My Lord, and my God!</hi> Nay, at his <hi>Aſcention</hi> he choſe not to vaniſh or ſuddenly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear, but gave the men of <hi>Galilee</hi> time to <hi>ſtand</hi> and <hi>gaze,</hi> ſubmitted his <hi>Motion</hi> to the <hi>Scrutiny</hi> of their <hi>Eyes,</hi> whilſt he was carried up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32405:38"/>by Angels and Clouds in all the <hi>leiſure</hi> of a <hi>Triumph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. We will conſider Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Truth in an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation to our <hi>Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the very diffini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Schools, <hi>viz.</hi> A <hi>Conformity of the Object</hi> with the <hi>Intellect.</hi> Here I dare not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture far. In this Science, or <hi>Mystery</hi> of <hi>Words,</hi> a very judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Abſtracter</hi> would find it a hard task to be any thing co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32405:38"/>without falling upon an <hi>Infinite Collection,</hi> an <hi>Eternal Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,</hi> or ſome ſuch like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictious &amp; <hi>ſelf-duelling terms. True Metaphiſicks</hi> is ſtill a <hi>Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratum</hi> in Philoſophy; for what we have hitherto recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the <hi>Scholasticks, Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites,</hi> and others, appears only like the Ghoſt and Phantaſm of ſeparated <hi>Reaſon</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted <hi>Senſe.</hi> If we lanch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>vaſt expanſion</hi> of their <hi>pure Abſtractions,</hi> we find but very little to terminate our
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32405:39"/>Apprehenſions, but our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating Heads ſeem pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to ſwim in an <hi>Infinite Vacuum,</hi> and all <hi>ſubstantial thought</hi> by little and little to leſſen, and paſs away into a <hi>strange Tranſcendency.</hi> I could tell you of a Truth of the Object or Entity, a Truth of Appearance, another of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and one more of the Intellect, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miracle, all theſe may be <hi>one,</hi> viz. an <hi>appearance</hi> or <hi>repreſentation of the Object to the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32405:39"/>Intellect;</hi> I could tell you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that beſides the Truth of <hi>apprehenſion,</hi> there is one of <hi>Judgment,</hi> another of <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> and theſe again either <hi>Mental</hi> or <hi>Verbal;</hi> I could tell you from the <hi>Lord Herbert,</hi> that there is an <hi>invincible Inſtinct</hi> of common Notions, the ſame that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> before him called an <hi>Intelligence of Principles;</hi> that there are ſome <hi>Sacroſancta Principia</hi> (as the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Perſon ſtiles them) which inform us, that there <hi>is a God,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:32405:40"/>that he ought to be <hi>Adored;</hi> but <hi>how,</hi> and in <hi>what manner,</hi> what will make our Worſhip acceptable, our Sacrifices, or our Prayers regarded, here his <hi>Inſtinct, Internal, External Senſe,</hi> and <hi>Intellect,</hi> with all their <hi>Analogies, Conditions,</hi> and <hi>Conſequences</hi> can give us no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter direction than the Finger of a <hi>Mercurial</hi> Statue, when we are puzling in a dark and crooked Alley. 'Tis not my buſineſs to give you a Cenſure of that <hi>Noble Mans Labours;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32405:40"/>Gaſſendus</hi> has done it already in an <hi>imperfect Epiſtle,</hi> wherein he has utterly renounced the Genius of his Nation, ſcarce allowing the Author one <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolary Complement;</hi> though 'tis to be preſumed, that when the Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> ſent him his Book, he expected he ſhould have returned the Applauſes of a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and not the Animadverſions of a <hi>Critick.</hi> Yet ſo it often happens, for another great <hi>Wit des Cartes</hi> met with the ſame Fate, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32405:41"/>from the ſame hand too. He grew ſo confident and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous of his <hi>Meditations,</hi> that he ſent out <hi>ſportive Challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> to invite <hi>Objections</hi> from all his Friends, till at laſt like one of his <hi>own Kings,</hi> he was quite <hi>baffled</hi> and ſlain amidſt his very <hi>Tilts</hi> and <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments.</hi> After the <hi>Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> have quite tired them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their Diviſions and ſubdiviſions, they are ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt as not to make <hi>Humane Intellect</hi> the <hi>adequate meaſure</hi> of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32405:41"/>Truth, but ultimately reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve it into a <hi>Conformity</hi> with the <hi>Divine Understanding,</hi> which a <hi>Platoniſt</hi> would after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner explain, That there is an Eternal mind, that compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the intelligible Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and <hi>Idea's</hi> of all things, whether actually exiſting, or poſſibly only; that compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends it ſelf, and all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of its own power, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an exemplar Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of the whole World, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32405:42"/>the ſame. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted, we are as much in the dark as ever; for unleſs this <hi>eternal mind</hi> ſhall vouchſafe to acquaint us what is <hi>conformable</hi> to his <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite unerring Underſtanding,</hi> we can have but little <hi>certainty</hi> of Truth.</p>
            <p>Now this is the peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Province of <hi>Revelation.</hi> And that it may appear how <hi>natural</hi> this <hi>Medium</hi> is, how ſuitable to the <hi>Univerſal conſent</hi> of Mankind, you may pleaſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32405:42"/>to reflect, that <hi>Revelation</hi> has been the true, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended foundation of all <hi>Knowledge</hi> whatſoever. No <hi>Religions,</hi> no <hi>Policies</hi> impoſed upon the World without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and retirements with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi> Not only <hi>Religions</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> but all <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> all noble <hi>Inventions</hi> have ever boaſted of their <hi>Aegeria's,</hi> their aſſiſting <hi>Daemons</hi> too.</p>
            <p>When the light of Nature, that firſt Revelation was diſtorted,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32405:43"/>and the unguided reaſon of the Idolatrous World had termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated all Divinity in the works of the Creation, <hi>then did God ſpeak at ſundry times, and in divers manners to the Fathers by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets;</hi> When the <hi>Gentiles</hi> would not learn of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> which was a conſtant viſible demonſtration of the <hi>Power, Providence,</hi> and <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of God, their Ignorance for ſome time was winked at, till at laſt God was pleaſed more fully to declare his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:32405:43"/>and <hi>Will</hi> by his <hi>Eternal Son,</hi> the brightneſs of his Fathers Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon, who brought Life and Immortality to light through the Goſpel. So that now the <hi>Bible</hi> is become the perfect Regiſter even of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion</hi> too, ſince all thoſe <hi>excellent truths,</hi> whith the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then World faintly hinted at, rather <hi>wiſh'd</hi> than <hi>believ'd,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they concern matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> or the Duties of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,</hi> are infallibly aſſured to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32405:44"/>us by the ſupernatural Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that God, whoſe veracity is eſtabliſhed by an infinite Knowledge, whereby he cannot be deceiv'd himſelf, and an eternal holineſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he can't deceive us. And to take away all complaints about Error, the obſcurity of things, and the imperfectneſs of our finite Underſtandings (thoſe bold Murmurs, which reverberate on Heaven and Providence it ſelf) we are Promiſed and Aſſured that the <hi>Third Perſon</hi> in the Trinity
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32405:44"/>will be with us to the end of the World to guide and direct us in all neceſſary Truth.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly, Carteſius</hi> goes farther than the Schoolmen. He uncatechizes himſef thro' a long ſeries of <hi>Dubitation;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents an Art to ſtifle Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Memory, ſtrips him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all his prejudices, only that he might put them on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in another dreſs, and preſent us with a nicer Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, a more <hi>ſplendid me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> of his <hi>Errors.</hi> For 'tis
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32405:45"/>certain that moſt of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd upon him again, not unlike to that which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomiſts obſerve, that if you grind any matter into too mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute a duſt, the little parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles will cling again, and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite</hi> by reaſon of a <hi>too exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite</hi> ſeparation. Wherefore after he had fanci'd the whole World a <hi>Faire-Land,</hi> Life a meer <hi>Dream,</hi> all Conſcious and thinking Nature but the deluſions of an <hi>evil Genius;</hi> after all this enchantment he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32405:45"/>can find nothing, that can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain to him any Truth but the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which will not ſuffer our faculties to be impoſed upon in their clear and evident perceptions, ſo that that which can give the beſt account of the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> juſtly claims the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this Criterion.</p>
            <p>And, that <hi>Revelation</hi> does ſo would be almoſt improper here to mention, but that the method of my Diſcourſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it. I ſhall inſtance on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32405:46"/>in one thing, but that the greateſt, the vaſt Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Heaven and Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the Second <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Incarnation,</hi> his taking our Humane Nature upon him, to Converſe with us, to Dye for us, for Us Sinners. A Myſtery of Love, which gave the very <hi>Angels</hi> new Anthems, a <hi>new Scene</hi> of <hi>Knowledg,</hi> and conſequently a <hi>new Heaven!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would not be thought to ſpeak againſt <hi>all Philoſophy,</hi> to declaim againſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32405:46"/>all Learning, any more than he that Preaches againſt a full Table, or exhorts to Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, would be thought to make Starving Orthodox, and Self-murder a Goſpel-Precept. For ſince <hi>Philoſophy</hi> is by moſt men allowed to be the requiſie improvement of our natural Faculties; ſince 'tis commendably made the great Employ and Study of our younger years, and the better Commerce of our more advanc'd Society; ſince ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32405:47"/>and almoſt meriting Charity hath built us Schools and Colledges for our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Receſs and Meditation, bequeathed us competent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, for the eaſie maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and tranquility of a <hi>Thinking Life,</hi> nobly endow'd our Profeſſors for more ſpeedy advances in Arts and Sciences; and ſince <hi>Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths</hi> with their prudent <hi>Laws</hi> and Conſtitutions have eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed to us our <hi>Univerſities,</hi> certainly we ought not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32405:47"/>
               <hi>Philoſophy</hi> with ſo cold a regard, as the <hi>Phanaticiſm</hi> of ſome, and the incapacity of others to attain ſo great an excellency, is ready to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane it with. But yet if we take a farther proſpect, and view it in its ultimate tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies we may with as equal reaſon blame its <hi>Adoration</hi> as its <hi>Contempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoſophy</hi> was intended, as our Colleges wherein 'tis taught, not to ſpend our our whole Age, 60 years and 10 in it, but to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32405:48"/>make it our paſſage to more ſolid attainments, to equippe our ſelves for more <hi>ſubstantial Knowledge.</hi> 'Tis but an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction, a Miniſtring Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment for <hi>Divinity,</hi> and we are firſt taught the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> that we may better underſtand the <hi>Sacred Character.</hi> 'Tis but a <hi>Jewiſh Canaan,</hi> Typical and ſignificative of a more Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Manſion, and may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a judicious Management ſerve to ſhadow out to us,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32405:48"/>though very imperfectly, the infinite Treaſures of revealed Wiſdom. So that the intent of my diſcourſe was only to ſhew, that whatever preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>Philoſophy</hi> or <hi>natural Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> could make for <hi>Truth</hi> or Certainty, yet <hi>Revelation</hi> (there being ſuch a thing granted by the <hi>Adverſary</hi>) laid fuller and more abundant claim to all thoſe Rules and Meaſures of Truth. But ſhould I now reckon up all the incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable characters of Truth,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32405:49"/>to <hi>Revelation,</hi> it would require a Volumn. I will only mention ſome few, and thoſe ſuch as lye within the compaſs of <hi>Philoſophical Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings,</hi> then anſwer an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection or two of the <hi>Natural-liſt,</hi> and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>Whatever <hi>Philoſophy</hi> or <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religion</hi> can truly arrive to in its beſt progreſs of <hi>Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> its higheſt exaltation, <hi>Revelation</hi> has all the benefit and evidence of <hi>that Light,</hi> beſides a farther and infallible
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32405:49"/>confirmation from <hi>Divine Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi> Moreover, the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> of the <hi>Object,</hi> peculiar to the matters of Revelation, gains a freer admittance, makes a ſtronger and more laſting impreſſion on the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, than any other common Motive whatever. For no man needs any other Argument than his own <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> to convince him, that <hi>Aſſent</hi> ariſeth more properly from the <hi>exceſſive worth</hi> of the <hi>Object</hi> than from the <hi>dry evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:32405:50"/>of <hi>Apprehenſion,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuity</hi> it ſelf. And that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, however in Philoſophy <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> may ſeem diſtinct, yet in <hi>Divinity</hi> they are all one; and the moſt <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted ſpeculation</hi> there, has a conſtant <hi>Morality</hi> annex'd to it, which always ſuperadd's the Recommendation of the <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> too. And how mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificently ſoever men para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe on <hi>Reaſon, Intelligible Ideas,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Verities,</hi> they are our <hi>Paſſions,</hi> that muſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32405:50"/>carry us to Heaven; our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and our Devotion, our Love, our Fear, and our Hopes; and our Reaſon and our Faith, only as joyn'd with theſe. 'Twas the zeal of the <hi>Affections,</hi> aſſiſted by the Holy Spirit, that reconcil'd <hi>Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> and reſcu'd the <hi>Bible</hi> from the <hi>Diocleſian Flames.</hi> There each holy Martyr would freely part with his Life, but not his <hi>Bible.</hi> That Sacred <hi>Depoſitum</hi> was all his Wealth, his World, his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32405:51"/>When his right hand was cut off, he ſeized it with his left; when that was gone too, he faſten'd on it with his Mouth, and amidſt his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſang Hallelujahs out of it; when his breath could no longer articulate his devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his panting heart ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd it, and when the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant graſped that, it fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with his Soul. Now ſearch all the Records, all the Catalogues of <hi>Stoicks,</hi> thoſe great <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:32405:51"/>of <hi>Death,</hi> and ſee if this can be parallell'd. We have read indeed of a Philoſopher, that offer'd up an <hi>Hecatomb</hi> for the <hi>invention</hi> of a <hi>Propoſition,</hi> but he would never have Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>himſelf</hi> for the <hi>Confirmation</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Naturaliſt</hi> tells us, we have no <hi>ſublime Notions</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> only knew his Name; whereas every Hebrew name of God is a pregnant <hi>Hierogli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick</hi> in his Theology, and that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32405:52"/>one word <hi>Jehova</hi> is a Body of Divinity. The Scriptures have acquainted us with ſo much of the Nature of God, as may ſufficiently inſpirit our <hi>Obedience;</hi> and thoſe, who have pretended to farther diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, have only opened a way to <hi>Hereſie, Enthuſiaſm,</hi> and even <hi>Atheiſm</hi> it ſelf. And we have reaſon to fear that thoſe curious and ſubtil Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of late about the <hi>Idea</hi> of a God, have done but little ſervice to the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32405:52"/>What the underſtanding in things of this Nature, like a clear Fountain, would natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reflect as it maintains its ordinary Current, when once examined and ſtirred, either defaces or diſtorts; and I am apt to think, that the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> and its <hi>abſolute Attributes</hi> are beſt known by the modeſt reflection of the firſt Thought. The moſt abſtracting Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſitian, that ſtudies them farther, does but think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into amazement, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32405:53"/>with the <hi>delaying Philoſopher,</hi> only loſes his God by a <hi>lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Procraſtination.</hi> But ſtill the ſame Adverſary urges that 'tis ſtrangely irrational to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent God Almighty with <hi>Paſſions</hi> and <hi>Senſes,</hi> which the Scriptures every where allow. This is diſingenious Sophiſtry; for he that makes the <hi>Objection</hi> cannot be ignorant of the <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</hi> That men ſhould quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with the condeſcentions of the Almighty! That when he is graciouſly pleaſed to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32405:53"/>ſpeak to them, they ſhould diſpute the <hi>Nature</hi> of his <hi>Voice!</hi> when he ſays, he has <hi>compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> on'em, they ſhould ask, where then are his <hi>Bowels!</hi> when he revokes a threatned Judgment, they ſhould plead, He cannot! Divine Animal! would'ſt thou be convers'd with in the Language of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity? wouldſt thou be treated with in the ineffable Dialect of Heaven? Alaſs! fond Creature, thou art E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemented and Organ'd for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32405:54"/>Apprehenſions, for a lower Commerce of percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Such immediate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plays of Divinity infinitely tranſcend the <hi>Analogy</hi> of thy Order, and the immoderate Glory of ſuch a Revelation would but abſorb thy Soul, and crack its <hi>Hypostaſis:</hi> Thou canſt not ſee God, and live.</p>
            <p>But ſtill the <hi>Natural Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> in the Scripture can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be pardoned; either that, or <hi>De Cartes</hi> muſt be falſe. However Men may flatter
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:32405:54"/>themſelves that they have Orbs and Circumvolutions of Souls Concentric to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, yet we may very rationally believe, that an exact Knowledge of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was never deſigned Man on this ſide of Heaven; it may poſſibly be reſerved for our <hi>Illuminated Faculties,</hi> and be an acceſſary of our Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification. The <hi>Eſſences</hi> of things can be the Object of no other than a <hi>Divine Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> and he that made the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32405:55"/>World, can only have a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Knowledge of it. What if Divine Providence, as a peculiar priviledge, granted to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acquaintance with Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet event hath ſhewn, that there was a kind of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragrammaton</hi> in it, that it was thought a thing too Sacred to be communicated to Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo that what they enjoyed was no <hi>Natural Acquiſition,</hi> but a <hi>Gracious Gift,</hi> not ſo much <hi>Science</hi> as <hi>Viſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:32405:55"/>
            <p>Though <hi>Carteſius</hi> in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Meteors</hi> has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured with <hi>Epicurus</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Deity from the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Region, and to deliver us up to the <hi>Providence</hi> of an <hi>Atmoſphere,</hi> yet God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thought fit to manifeſt his <hi>Omnipotence</hi> to <hi>Job</hi> from that place rather than from the <hi>Heaven</hi> of <hi>Heavens.</hi> What is the end we propoſe of our enquiries into Nature? Is it to ſerve and gratify our Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity? That we will not own.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32405:56"/>Is it to plume our <hi>Pride?</hi> That we dare not own. Then it can be no other than to ſettle in us a due reverence and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the <hi>Wiſdom, Power,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of God. Now all this is <hi>Pathetically</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to us in Scripture, ſince it may very effectually be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by an humble Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the <hi>Exiſtences</hi> of things, their more <hi>open Qualities,</hi> and their obvious <hi>Relations.</hi> The conſideration of the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial parts and uſes of ſenſible
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32405:56"/>Nature (the very Mode and Method of the Scripture's Philoſophy) has, we know, in a meer Heathens Breaſt kindled Admiration into an <hi>Hymn;</hi> But I never yet read of any <hi>Anthems</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed from the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Atoms. Who can Spell the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs out of the Principles of <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> where he gives us the Origen of all things in a Puppet-play, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32405:57"/>all the works of God according to the <hi>bruit Laws</hi> of <hi>Mechaniſm,</hi> and allows no other Operations in <hi>Vital Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> then what he finds paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell'd in <hi>German Clockwork?</hi> Whereas, who can without holy Affections peruſe the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Majeſty of <hi>Moſe</hi>'s account? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where he deſcribes the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Fiat</hi> in a Phraſe almoſt commenſurate to the Dignity of the Creation, that ſome <hi>Rabbins</hi> have thought his very
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32405:57"/>Style, as well as Senſe to have been inſpir'd.</p>
            <p>They are our too eager diſquiſitions after the <hi>Internal</hi> Verities of things that have led the Witty World into ſo large a Field of <hi>Scepticiſm.</hi> Men muſt be preſſing and breaking into the <hi>Receſses</hi> of Nature, as that <hi>Conqueror</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore into the <hi>Sanctum Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> then miſtake the thing, return diſſatisfied, cry all is <hi>Pageantry,</hi> and that we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Clouds. I had rather
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:32405:58"/>read the <hi>Aſtoniſhments</hi> of <hi>Job,</hi> when God poſes him through the whole <hi>Creation,</hi> then all the bold explications of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Daemons.</hi> I had rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>Rain-bow</hi> as the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> of God's Mercy, then the Sun's Light; and when I call to mind, that <hi>Thunder</hi> throughout the Scriptures is ſtiled his <hi>Mighty Voice,</hi> I'm ſatisfi'd at what I <hi>Tremble,</hi> and though this may debaſe my <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> yet it heightens my <hi>Divinty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:32405:58"/>
            <p>If any man is not yet ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied what is <hi>Truth,</hi> let him but ſeriouſly reflect on his <hi>Death-Bed,</hi> and the Day of <hi>Judgement,</hi> and then I'm per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded hee'l need no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; When the Gayety of <hi>Fancy</hi> forſakes him, and the Proſperity of <hi>Invention</hi> gives no reliſh; when his <hi>Paſſions</hi> and <hi>Appetites</hi> grow languid from the impotence of <hi>Blood,</hi> and his <hi>Brain</hi> becomes too weak for the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> then will he call for a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:32405:59"/>Portion of Scripture to eaſe his Conſcience, a drop from the Fountain of Living Water to cool his tongue. Then ſet him on the higheſt Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Metaphyſics,</hi> and from thence give him the Raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proſpect of all the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> of <hi>Humane Learning,</hi> all the <hi>Glorys</hi> of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> yet he will not Worſhip, not I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolize one glittering Notion, not part with one ſingle Text for a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. When the laſt Fire ſhall make Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:32405:59"/>confeſs it ſelf to be no <hi>God,</hi> the Sun and Moon be darkned, the Elements and Stars melt with fervent heat, and run together into one great <hi>Vortex</hi> of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and when the whole Volumn of the Creation ſhall be ſhrieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up like a Scroll of Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then ſhall the <hi>Holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> be opened, its everlaſting Truths unfolded, and though Heaven and Earth paſs away yet not one <hi>Iota</hi> of that ſhall periſh.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:32405:60"/>
            <p>Go now, and neglect Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the receptacle of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and departed Souls, for the viſible Heaven of <hi>Orbs</hi> and <hi>Planets,</hi> and loſe the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atific Viſion for that through a <hi>Tube!</hi> Go, thou that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gereſt after <hi>Humane Learning,</hi> go! make a vaſt Progreſs in ſpecious Errors, and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acquire to thy ſelf a deep-read Confuſion of thought! loſe all good Senſe by a multiplicity of Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, grow gray under a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32405:60"/>Problem, and make thy Grave in the Duſt of <hi>Geometry!</hi> let the reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology, and the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſties ſwallow up thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Salvation!</hi> let the uncertainties of Proſane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors attend thee on thy Death-Bed, and with their reſtleſs Tumult add a <hi>Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> to thy Feaver! then let thy Learned Aſhes be kept in Urns, and thy great Name be read in Annals. Yet for all
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32405:61"/>this know, O man, that <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> gave thee thy <hi>Pompous Thoughts, Ariſtotle</hi> thy <hi>Sagacity</hi> in Invention, and <hi>Euclid</hi> thy Mighty <hi>Demonſtrations;</hi> In a word, that <hi>Heathens</hi> gave thee all thy <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>Curſe</hi> of <hi>Babel</hi> thy <hi>Languages</hi> to expreſs it. Go therefore ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Captivate all thy <hi>Thoughts</hi> to the poſitions of <hi>Faith,</hi> thy whole <hi>Heart</hi> to the embracement of the Goſpel, and let the frequent Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on <hi>Sin, Death,</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:32405:61"/>macerate thy <hi>bold Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi> into an humble <hi>contrition</hi> of underſtanding.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:62"/>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:32405:62"/>
            <head>POPERY One great Cauſe of ATHEISM.</head>
            <q>
               <hi>OMnis</hi> Haereſis <hi>cum ad</hi> Atheiſmum <hi>delapſa eſt, per ſapientem Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetam, quales in Italiâ fuêrunt</hi> Thomas, Dominicus, <hi>Scotus &amp; alii, in</hi> Veritatis <hi>viam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducitur.</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:32405:63"/>
               <bibl>Tho. Campanelle <hi>De Monarchiâ Hiſpan. Cap.</hi> 30.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>The foundations of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual</hi> World are theſe four.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 2. <hi>Morality.</hi> 3. <hi>Civil Government.</hi> 4. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> And that each of theſe <hi>Pillars</hi> is remov'd, <hi>undermin'd,</hi> or out of courſe, either thro' the <hi>ſly Machinations,</hi> or open <hi>aſſaults</hi> of our implacable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, the Papiſts; who either act themſelves with <hi>declared Malignity,</hi> or put <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32405:63"/>Engines</hi> into other mens hands, a little <hi>reflection</hi> on the ſeveral <hi>Heads</hi> may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Foundation</hi> which they have <hi>diſordered</hi> is <hi>Reaſon</hi> in <hi>general.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I preſume there are very few ignorant how large a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion <hi>Scepticiſm</hi> has of late obtained among our inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Athenians,</hi> and how ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly it has been introduced under the Titles of <hi>free Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,</hi> and a <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:32405:64"/>a vindication of Captiv'd Truth, and an <hi>Advancement</hi> of <hi>Learning;</hi> a redeeming of <hi>Humane Reaſon</hi> from the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> of <hi>Barbarous Terms,</hi> and the dotages of <hi>antiquated</hi> ſenſe; And altho' at firſt ſight there may ſeem little or no deſign of the <hi>Roman Party</hi> in introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing this <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Models,</hi> and theſe <hi>diſguiſes</hi> of <hi>Reaſoning</hi> amongſt us; becauſe they have ſometimes ſeemed to put a <hi>check</hi> to theſe <hi>attempts</hi> by their <hi>Inquiſitions</hi> and <hi>Cenfures,</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:32405:64"/>and becauſe they themſelves have been unhappily baffled in many of their <hi>Doctrines,</hi> even according to theſe <hi>new Modes</hi> of <hi>Arguing,</hi> by thoſe who have had skill enough to fix to themſelves a <hi>ſyſtem</hi> of <hi>ſolid Reaſon</hi> in ſpite of all their <hi>amazing Sophistry,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſive Shapes;</hi> yet if we allow our thoughts a little <hi>Hiſtorical Range,</hi> we may ſtill imagine that the <hi>Plot</hi> was laid long ſince, and that our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> with a <hi>Spaniſh Providence</hi> did
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:32405:65"/>long ago contrive and plant that <hi>Malice,</hi> whoſe <hi>Maturity</hi> and <hi>happy growth</hi> they hop'd their <hi>Poſterity</hi> would one day enjoy; and this has been their acknowledg'd <hi>Deſign</hi> to ſome of our <hi>Travellers,</hi> to whom they have freely confeſſed that it has been their chief <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs</hi> to cheriſh the <hi>inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive humor</hi> of the <hi>Protestants</hi> with <hi>new Models,</hi> to dazle their <hi>Curioſity</hi> with <hi>falſe Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances,</hi> that they might crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them into <hi>Sects,</hi> bring
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:32405:65"/>ſome to <hi>indifferency</hi> in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, others to <hi>Scepticiſm</hi> and down-right <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> becauſe, ſay they, the minds of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> muſt lie <hi>Fallow</hi> before we can ſow our <hi>Seeds</hi> and <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> with ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Now it is well known how irreconcilable the firſt <hi>Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> in Religion were to the <hi>Philoſophy</hi> of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> with what bitterneſs of Style <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> and their reſpective <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers</hi> decry'd the Writings of the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> as the only ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:32405:66"/>of the <hi>Roman Corruptions,</hi> inſomuch that <hi>Bucer</hi> made it his conſtant challenge <hi>Tolle Thomam, &amp; Eccleſiam Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſubvertam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beware of vain <hi>Philoſophy</hi> was one of the chief <hi>Doctrines</hi> which rang through <hi>Heidle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> and the firſt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were ſo ſcared with thoſe <hi>Declamations</hi> againſt <hi>World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdom,</hi> that they eſteem'd every <hi>Sentence,</hi> which was not <hi>Scripture-phraſe</hi> to be meer <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation;</hi> a <hi>Syllogiſm</hi> was the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:32405:66"/>very <hi>Mystery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> and <hi>School-diſtinctions</hi> as <hi>ranck Magick,</hi> as <hi>Mathematicks</hi> in the <hi>Tenth Century.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now things being brought to this height, and ſuch Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies againſt <hi>Scholastick Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> being every where enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, there could not be a more effectual way of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Philoſophy</hi> into Credit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, (which <hi>Philoſophy</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes above half of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church) than by the invention of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:32405:67"/>
               <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what deſtructive and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to thoſe of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and by ordering it ſo; that thoſe perſons ſhould appear no friends to the <hi>Roman Party,</hi> who were the firſt promoters of them; for by theſe means the <hi>inquiſitive</hi> men in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Churches</hi> might with great ſafety to their Religion (as it then appeared to them) embrace and carry on the new diſcoveries of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and introduce that <hi>Liberty</hi> of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32405:67"/>Philoſophizing which expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hath now ſhown to be the moſt deſtructive <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> that could be thought of to unſettle all the true <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of <hi>ſolid Reaſon,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our <hi>half-taught Youth</hi> in <hi>wild Diſputes, weak Cavils,</hi> and <hi>everlaſting Scepticiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For now what hinders but that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> (that diſtorted <hi>Anagram</hi> of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi>) may paſs for <hi>true Goſpel</hi> notwithſtanding all the Remonſtrances and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:32405:68"/>evidences of our <hi>Senſes,</hi> which according to the <hi>Dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> of <hi>Des Cartes</hi> are the moſt <hi>Fallible</hi> and deluding witneſſes we can make uſe of, which miſtake ſomething in every Object they converſe with, and occaſion <hi>Error</hi> by their moſt material reports; tho' it muſt be confeſſed that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the more ignorant <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots</hi> in <hi>France</hi> were very Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of this man's <hi>writings</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in reſpect of their <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi> and therefore
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32405:68"/>they often adviſed him to lay in good <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Epiſt.</hi> Des Cartes <hi>l.</hi> 2. Ep. 3.4.53, 54, &amp;c.</note> ſecurity in his <hi>new Method</hi> for the <hi>Philoſophy</hi> of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and to be very cautious of maintaining any thing in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of thoſe <hi>Peripatetic Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents</hi> which they had ſo long <hi>Ador'd,</hi> and which his <hi>Modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> might ſeem to cancel; and truly we may believe that his <hi>Metaphyſical Doubtings</hi> have pretry well expiated for his other <hi>Innovations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:32405:69"/>
            <p>But beſides the Abſurdities of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> which <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm</hi> hath ſo much befriended, all the <hi>Rational</hi> motives of <hi>Credibility,</hi> and the truth of <hi>Moral Certainty</hi> are by the ſame means rendred precarious and weak, and <hi>Infallibility</hi> made to appear the only ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For when the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> had aſſerted a <hi>moderate</hi> uſe of, and dependance on their <hi>Reaſon</hi> in <hi>Divine matters;</hi> when they had reſcu'd themſelves from
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:32405:69"/>the intolerable <hi>Bondage</hi> of a <hi>blind Obedience,</hi> and the unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Conduct of an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Faith;</hi> What more <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Artifice</hi> could the <hi>Polititians</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> invent to weaken theſe proceedings, than to render that <hi>ſtrong Aid</hi> and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of our <hi>Religion</hi> the moſt <hi>uncertain</hi> and contemptible <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument</hi> we could make uſe of; or elſe to advance that <hi>inadequate Rule</hi> as the only <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> of <hi>all</hi> that is <hi>Divine?</hi> both which ways are
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:32405:70"/>equally deſtructive of that <hi>ſobriety</hi> of its uſe which our <hi>Church</hi> maintains. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we find how <hi>Eloquent</hi> and plauſible they are in many of their Writings when they touch upon that <hi>Topic</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing our <hi>own Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Underſtanding;</hi> how they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blazon its <hi>Infirmities, Deceptions, falſe Inferences,</hi> and <hi>Judgments,</hi> making all the <hi>Faculties</hi> of Man, even after the beſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of <hi>Art,</hi> of <hi>Virtue,</hi> and of <hi>Grace,</hi> a more deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:32405:70"/>
               <hi>Maſs</hi> of <hi>Corruption,</hi> than the ſevereſt <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> in his deſcriptions of <hi>Original Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from ſuch encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as theſe our <hi>Atheiſtical Wits</hi> have borrowed their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter Blaſphemies</hi> againſt <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature,</hi> improving the <hi>Notion,</hi> and growing <hi>Luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> in their <hi>Satyrs</hi> againſt the Nobleſt <hi>Workmanſhip</hi> in the <hi>viſible</hi> Creation; whilſt their beſt <hi>Panegyrics</hi> have been ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilely imployed on the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative Felicity</hi> of <hi>inferior Beings,</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:32405:71"/>on the <hi>Tranquility</hi> of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and the <hi>unerring Instinct</hi> of <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Nature;</hi> endeavouring by theſe <hi>Poetic Phrenſies</hi> to make vain and ridiculous the <hi>Concluſions</hi> of the Learned, the <hi>Experiences</hi> of the <hi>Prudent,</hi> and the <hi>Counſels</hi> of the <hi>Pious;</hi> for theſe revilings of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Aged Dictates</hi> are the little <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies</hi> which take with the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual and the debauched, with thoſe who have ſuch a <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Knowledg</hi> of things as to think that none have more,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:32405:71"/>and who love to meaſure all the <hi>Certainty</hi> and <hi>Evidence</hi> of <hi>Reaſon</hi> by their Schemes of <hi>Railery</hi> and <hi>Illuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then there are ſome <hi>Contemplative</hi> Men, of more <hi>ſullen Tempers</hi> than to be <hi>Jeer'd</hi> out of their Conceptions, and to have their <hi>Syſtems</hi> baffled by the Captious and frivolous <hi>Sceptick;</hi> ſuch as out of a <hi>Pride</hi> of <hi>Dictating,</hi> and a ſuppoſed <hi>Superiority</hi> of Parts challenge <hi>Philoſophy</hi> as their <hi>Province,</hi> cry up their own private Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:32405:72"/>for <hi>establiſhed Actions,</hi> and explain <hi>Univerſal Nature</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own individual <hi>Complexions;</hi> wherefore that there might be alſo an <hi>agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> bait for the <hi>Confident</hi> and <hi>Dogmatical</hi> man, the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Demonſtration</hi> muſt be highly <hi>advanced</hi> by the <hi>Factors</hi> for <hi>Rome,</hi> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than <hi>ſelf-evident Principles</hi> muſt juſtifie our <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſion</hi> to Religion: and to create a <hi>Reverence</hi> for <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> and the <hi>particular Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions</hi>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:32405:72"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> and alſo a <hi>Confuſion</hi> and <hi>uncertainty</hi> in the <hi>Proteſtants Principles,</hi> the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi> and <hi>Diſputers</hi> of the Age muſt be ſuborned to cry up <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Judge</hi> of <hi>Controverſies,</hi> the only Tribunal of all <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Falſhood;</hi> whatſoever is above that muſt be either <hi>Phantaſm</hi> or <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and all thoſe <hi>Sublimities</hi> in Religion which cannot ſubmit to the <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Syllogiſm,</hi> muſt be reproached as the <hi>Phrenſies</hi> of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:32405:73"/>an <hi>overheated Devotion,</hi> or the <hi>Viſions</hi> of an Hermits Cell, all the <hi>Pelagian</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions muſt be induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly encouraged to that <hi>Height,</hi> that the <hi>Protestants</hi> ſhall ſeem to have no <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> among them, no <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> unleſs they return to the <hi>Definitions</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Roman See.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Intellectual World</hi> which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have diſturbed, is <hi>Morality.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:32405:73"/>
            <p>In <hi>Morality</hi> there are but theſe <hi>two general Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Nature of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. The <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to accommodate the mind of Man thereunto.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As for the <hi>First,</hi> 'Tis well known how the <hi>Flatterers</hi> of the <hi>Roman Court,</hi> the <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> and all ſuch as treat of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:32405:74"/>
               <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> have with <hi>mighty Attributes,</hi> and a <hi>Divinity</hi> of Terms, made the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Arbitrarious</hi> Judge of all <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> determiner of all <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Vice,</hi> affirming that he can change the nature of <hi>Moral</hi> things according to his <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> for ſo their more <hi>eminent</hi> Champion aſſerts, that if the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould miſtake in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending Vices, and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Virtues, the Church would be bound to believe
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:32405:74"/>thoſe Vices to be good, and thoſe Virtues to be evil, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe would ſin againſt Conſcience, <hi>Bel. de Pontif. l.</hi> 4.6.5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. and though ſome of them plead the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility</hi> of the <hi>Suppoſal,</hi> yet ſad experience hath confirm'd the matter, and clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated how the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in ſundry inſtances has Canoniz'd the broadeſt <hi>Impiety</hi> for <hi>Virtue,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice;</hi> nay, for that <hi>exceſs</hi> of Virtue which they call <hi>Merit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:32405:75"/>
            <p>And hence it is, that the Idolizers of <hi>Monarchy</hi> with equal Flattery have attributed the ſame Prerogative to <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Princes,</hi> making their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations a <hi>publick Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and their Edicts <hi>Eternal Truth:</hi> and generally all thoſe Monſtrous Opinions, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious Abſurdities concerning the Notion of <hi>Good,</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> which at this day diſturb the World, have taken their Riſe and Meaſures from the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:32405:75"/>
            <p>But then <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorably manifeſt, with what <hi>Confuſions, Obſcurities,</hi> and <hi>Diſtortions</hi> they have darkned and peplex'd the moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and neceſſary Rules and preſcriptions of <hi>Morality:</hi> and we have now many Volumns extant to maintain this Charge againſt them.</p>
            <p>The only <hi>natural</hi> Spring and Foundation of all the good Offices of <hi>Humanity</hi> is certainly <hi>Love,</hi> which is a conſtant thirſt and endeavour
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:32405:76"/>of being <hi>largely beneficial,</hi> of extending all our <hi>Capacities,</hi> to the ſervice of our <hi>Brethren:</hi> But now inſtead of this <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Principle</hi> of all our <hi>Moral Actions,</hi> the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and <hi>Barbarous Dominion;</hi> their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> and daily <hi>Practices</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict not only that eſpecial <hi>Christian Precept</hi> of <hi>Univerſal Charity,</hi> but all the firſt <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs</hi> of <hi>Natural Affection!</hi> they declare and proſecute Revenge and Murder, not
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:32405:76"/>only in reſpect of <hi>meer ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations,</hi> and <hi>undeterminable Modes,</hi> but even of thick and palpable <hi>Contradictions</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cleareſt <hi>Northern Judgement</hi> we can make; which we muſt confeſs to be the only <hi>Luminary</hi> next to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> which in this <hi>Climate</hi> we are guided by. How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary have they made the exerciſe of <hi>Virtue</hi> and an <hi>Holy Life</hi> by turning the <hi>abſolute</hi> Commands of God into <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> and <hi>Admonition,</hi> by diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:32405:77"/>
               <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> into an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Jewiſh</hi> Obedience, or a <hi>low Order</hi> or <hi>Precepts</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſecure Heaven, and a <hi>ſuper-errogating perfection</hi> for thoſe only who aſpire to the upper Seats, and Dignities of Paradice: By Interpreting all the <hi>Additions</hi> to, and <hi>Completi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Law</hi> to be only ſome more <hi>ſplendid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals</hi> and Recommendations of an <hi>higher Degree</hi> of Virtue, and by evacuating all the moſt excellent and neceſſary <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:32405:77"/>of our Saviours <hi>Sermon</hi> on the <hi>Mount,</hi> whilſt they make it appear only an <hi>Heroical Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> of <hi>Counſels</hi> for the <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly</hi> and retired.</p>
            <p>What an encouragement have the Vitious from that unwarrantable diſtinction of <hi>Sins,</hi> into <hi>Mortal</hi> and <hi>Venial!</hi> eſpecially when they make not only thoſe ſins Venial in their <hi>own Nature</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from <hi>Infirmity, Surreption, ſtrong Paſſion,</hi> and <hi>Education,</hi> but the moſt <hi>dreadful Catalogue</hi>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:32405:78"/>of <hi>Iniquity</hi> that can be thought on, ſuch as <hi>Blaſphemy, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation, Murder, Fornication, Perfidiouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> with ſome little <hi>qualifications,</hi> muſt be ſum'd up under that <hi>ſoft de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a Shop of <hi>Authorized Licentiouſneſs</hi> is their <hi>Caſuistical Divinity!</hi> whereas <hi>Caſes</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> at the beſt are but a <hi>Spurious</hi> ſort of Divinity, for they being generally termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the <hi>loweſt</hi> degree of <hi>goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:32405:78"/>thing but the <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie</hi> and <hi>Infirm</hi> Nature, ſome <hi>Charitable Proviſions</hi> in Religion for <hi>declining Virtue.</hi> But in this <hi>practical Divinity</hi> of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> there is ſuch a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> ſuch a Conſecrating of Villany by the <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> or rather the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of the <hi>Intention,</hi> and ſuch <hi>compaſſionate Circumſtances</hi> to be met with among their <hi>Doctors</hi> to render the moſt dreadful Tranſgreſſions <hi>ſlight</hi> and <hi>veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> to palliate and ſtupifie the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:32405:79"/>moſt <hi>juſt</hi> Remorſes of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Sinners;</hi> ſuch a <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> of <hi>Uucleanneſs</hi> in their <hi>Caſes</hi> on the <hi>ſeventh Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> where their determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations concerning <hi>Pleaſure</hi> are many times as looſe and Voluptuous as the Doctrines of <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> and <hi>Epicurus;</hi> in a word, there is ſuch a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Politick compliance</hi> with all thoſe <hi>Vitious Tempers</hi> by which that <hi>Faction</hi> is upheld, that if that be <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> which they profeſs, then the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:32405:79"/>have nothing but <hi>Honeſt Heatheniſm</hi> to govern their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> by.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Pillar</hi> of the <hi>Intellectual World</hi> which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> have diſordered, is <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this of late hath been ſo common an Argument both from <hi>Pulpit</hi> and <hi>Preſs,</hi> and is ſo notoriouſly evident both from their <hi>Eſtabliſhed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> and <hi>continual Practices,</hi> that a very few obſervations, and <hi>Remembrances</hi> may be
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:32405:80"/>thought ſufficient to diſpatch this <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly reflect how the <hi>Romanists</hi> have been the great diſturbers of <hi>Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. By <hi>perplexing</hi> its true <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and fundamental <hi>Riſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. By <hi>Weakning</hi> all its <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> and eſſential <hi>ſecurities.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:32405:80"/>
            <p n="1">I. By <hi>perplexing</hi> its true <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and fundamental <hi>Riſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well known how the warm pretenſions of <hi>Rome</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the power of <hi>Princes</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> matters hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged its <hi>Champions</hi> on the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution and <hi>vilifying</hi> even of their <hi>Temporal Juriſdiction</hi> too; and encouraged them to make all <hi>Civil Soveraignty</hi> precarious and depending, either on the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> that <hi>Monſtrous head</hi> of Anr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy;
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:32405:81"/>or on the pleaſure of the <hi>Multitude,</hi> that Monſtrous <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of <hi>Confuſion:</hi> whence their <hi>Political Writings</hi> are every where full of large Pleas for <hi>Rebellion,</hi> of ſpecious Colours and Incitements for <hi>Ambitious</hi> and <hi>Aſpiring</hi> Men; whilſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the <hi>Solemn Ordinance</hi> of God, the <hi>Natural, Jewiſh,</hi> and <hi>Christian</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Subjection,</hi> they have amuſed the World with groundleſs &amp; imaginary forms of Empire, with ſubtill and pernitious Schemes of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:32405:81"/>Strife, Pride, and eternal Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: and we may with much certainty averr, that all thoſe <hi>eager Contentions</hi> in our late <hi>dark Age,</hi> concerning <hi>Civil Authority, where</hi> and in <hi>whom</hi> the <hi>Supreme Power</hi> ſhould be placed, what was its <hi>Original,</hi> its <hi>Nature,</hi> its <hi>Extent?</hi> how far <hi>Obedience</hi> was required, in what circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it <hi>ceaſed,</hi> when <hi>reſiſtance</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a <hi>Duty,</hi> and ſuch like extravagancies of <hi>Stated mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> were nouriſhed and maintained by <hi>Jeſuitical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions;</hi>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:32405:82"/>particularly, that pretence of making uſe of the Kings <hi>Authority</hi> againſt his <hi>Perſon,</hi> was a noted Stratagem in the <hi>Holy League</hi> of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. They have weakned all the neceſſary and eſſential <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities</hi> of <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the <hi>Rational</hi> ſecurity that is in Government ariſes,</p>
            <p n="1">I. From the <hi>Natural Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of Good and Evil, of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Equity, ſeated in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Subjects Breaſt.</p>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:32405:82"/>
            <p n="2">II. From the <hi>Civil Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> which is ſuperinduced by the obligation of an <hi>Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>First Security</hi> which conſiſts in <hi>Natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> we have already inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in our <hi>Topic</hi> of <hi>Morality</hi> how miſerably the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have under-min'd <hi>that Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> by making it truckle to the determination and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Pope. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that which we call the <hi>Civil Conſcience,</hi> which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:32405:83"/>from the obligation of an <hi>Oath,</hi> depends chiefly on the <hi>Natural one,</hi> [for he who has not a <hi>primary</hi> Sence of good and evil as he ſtands in <hi>Relation</hi> to God, will have little regard to his <hi>Covenants</hi> with Man, when either his <hi>Interest,</hi> his <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> or his <hi>Humor</hi> ſhall ſolicit to the contrary] yet have they attempted by farther <hi>Evaſions</hi> perfectly to deſtroy the <hi>whole deſign</hi> of an <hi>Oath,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Remonſtrances of <hi>Natural Conſcience;</hi> and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:32405:83"/>that either in preventing its ever taking hold of men, by their Doctrine of <hi>Equivocation;</hi> or elſe in ſhifting off its Force and Authority by the <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations</hi> of their Popes. And is it not an amazing Subject to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fider, that that <hi>Act</hi> which the Heathens had in ſuch mighty Reverence, which <hi>Cicero</hi> calls a <hi>Religious Affirmation in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God,</hi> the <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> which is taken with that dreadful Solemnity of calling on the Almighty to be
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:32405:84"/>an immediate Aſſerter of the Truth and an Avenger of the Perjury, and which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath condeſcended to as a <hi>Security</hi> to his own <hi>Veracity,</hi> that I ſay this <hi>Compendium</hi> of <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> ſhould lay no more real Tie, and Reſtraint on Men, through the <hi>Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Reſerves,</hi> and <hi>permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> than the Dreams of Bondage, or the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Chains of Lovers! In a word, the whole civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of <hi>England,</hi> and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:32405:84"/>Countries in our Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances is according to the Principles of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> no other than a Confederacy and an agreement of <hi>Robbers:</hi> for they hold that we have no <hi>King,</hi> no <hi>Subjects,</hi> no <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> no <hi>Laws,</hi> no <hi>Liberties,</hi> no <hi>Properties:</hi> and indeed none of the Reſt, becauſe not the <hi>last.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſuch are the <hi>Roman Principles,</hi> their continual <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evidence, eſpecially this
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:32405:85"/>late <hi>Helliſh Plot,</hi> the <hi>diſcovery</hi> and <hi>prevention</hi> of which hath in a manner engroſſed the whole <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>united Saga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi> of ſucceſſive <hi>Parliaments;</hi> and yet the Vein runs <hi>deep</hi> ſtill, the <hi>amazement</hi> is ſtill <hi>great</hi> even on the <hi>awakened</hi> Senſe of the Nation. Surely our Enemies thought to entitle <hi>Heaven</hi> to their Plot, even by placing it ſo low; as thoſe who dig be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Centre</hi> are ſaid to dig <hi>upwards.</hi> The unfolding of this <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> ſeems a buſineſs
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:32405:85"/>too <hi>unweildy</hi> for the raſhneſs of <hi>Haſt,</hi> it requires the ſlow ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of <hi>working Engines,</hi> and a <hi>temperate Detection;</hi> that its pure, unmingled <hi>Malice</hi> may be drawn out with leiſure and obſervation, and all Mankind may have a <hi>Calm</hi> and <hi>Judicious</hi> view of the whole <hi>Anatomy</hi> of its Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>Surely our <hi>Natives</hi> without a <hi>Foraign</hi> degeneracy, without an <hi>Importation</hi> of Sin, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been guilty to ſuch a
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:32405:86"/>Forlornneſs, could never have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned ſuch contradictions to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Nature;</hi> they could not without the aids of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice have entailed <hi>Revenge</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Poſterity,</hi> and bequeathed their Nephews the <hi>Reverſion</hi> of Murther! This is <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Offence</hi> to out-ſin <hi>Probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> to appear Innocent, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch exceſs, Inhumane.</p>
            <p>That ſuch <hi>Religious Butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> ſhould be contrived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, ſo <hi>Juſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Merciful</hi> a King.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:32405:86"/>
            <p>For though his younger years came roughly on amidſt the Rage and Fury of a <hi>Civil War;</hi> though He had been juſtly exaſperated with the moſt Barbarous Murder of a <hi>Father;</hi> the beſt of <hi>Fathers;</hi> the beſt of <hi>Kings!</hi> that we had reaſon to expect his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn like that of a Gyant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with Wine, full of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, Revenge, and Slaughter, yet has he <hi>ruled</hi> our Kingdom as ſome <hi>Angel</hi> is ſuppoſed to rule a <hi>Sphere;</hi> his
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:32405:87"/>Government has been as <hi>gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> as that of an <hi>Intelligence,</hi> and his Edicts as mild as the Laws of Reaſon. When he might have called down Fire from Heaven on his <hi>unnatural Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> he choſe to ſend up <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe</hi> thither; and has not ſo much <hi>Puniſh'd</hi> as <hi>Atton'd</hi> for their <hi>Rebellions.</hi> And behold! when he was labouring to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite all <hi>Europe,</hi> to ſoften the incomplyances of <hi>Armed Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires,</hi> and to reconcile the <hi>Jealouſies</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> that he
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:32405:87"/>himſelf ſhould be made the <hi>publick Mark,</hi> and the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> abroad only give leiſure to the <hi>Treacheries</hi> of his own <hi>Court!</hi> whilſt the <hi>Ambitious</hi> and the <hi>Cruel</hi> lye emboſom'd in the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> of their <hi>Slaves,</hi> are honoured with <hi>Panegyricks</hi> and <hi>Triumphal Arches;</hi> as if only an <hi>open War</hi> could Fence off <hi>ſecret Treaſons,</hi> as the <hi>Plague</hi> is ſaid to keep out all other <hi>Diſtempers;</hi> and that <hi>Clemency,</hi> that great <hi>property</hi> that diſtinguiſhes a King of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:32405:88"/>
               <hi>Men</hi> from a King of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> ſhould render Loyalty <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible,</hi> and rob the Crown of its <hi>Prerogatives!</hi> yet ſo men have <hi>Murmured</hi> againſt <hi>Providence</hi> it ſelf becauſe of its <hi>Long-ſufferings,</hi> and raſhly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced there was no <hi>God,</hi> becauſe he was <hi>ſo Merciful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Heaven hath with <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Miracles</hi> aſſured us, that <hi>our King</hi> is too <hi>Dear a pledge</hi> to be delivered over to the Fury of an <hi>Aſſaſſinate:</hi> He who was protected by the <hi>ſhade</hi> of an
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:32405:88"/>
               <hi>Oak,</hi> cannot be leſs ſecure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Coverings</hi> of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty:</hi> ſo <hi>David</hi> could never have faln by the Spear of <hi>Saul,</hi> for his <hi>preſervation</hi> was upheld by <hi>Propheſie.</hi> Wherefore let the Mountains of <hi>Gilboah</hi> be fruitful, and the Inhabitants of the Iſles rejoyce, for behold our moſt <hi>Gracious Soveraign</hi> ſtill lives! and may he <hi>live,</hi> to grow <hi>old</hi> in Empire, to bleſs his Nation with <hi>Aged Hands,</hi> to make his <hi>Council</hi> ſtill wiſer by the experience of his <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:32405:89"/>and all <hi>Posterity</hi> amazed with the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of his <hi>protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Intellectual World,</hi> which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, is <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having already manifeſted how the <hi>Romanists</hi> have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted <hi>Reaſon,</hi> defaced <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,</hi> and undermined <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> our laſt <hi>Topic, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> (of which theſe three are no inconſiderable <hi>Branches</hi>) may ſeem in a great meaſure
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:32405:89"/>to have been already hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; but however there is a <hi>peculiar</hi> conſideration reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for <hi>this head</hi> which conſiſts in charging them with thoſe <hi>impious</hi> and intolerable <hi>Abuſes</hi> which they have offered to <hi>Divine Revelation</hi> and the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures</hi> in general: For what <hi>Difficulties, Obſcurities,</hi> and uncertainties have they aſcribed to that <hi>Eaſie, Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous,</hi> and <hi>Infallible</hi> Rule! that they might deter the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> from making it
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:32405:90"/>their <hi>Canon,</hi> and advance their own <hi>unwritten Traditions</hi> into its place? they eſteem our <hi>Tranſlated Bible</hi> to be only an <hi>Aſylum</hi> for <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks,</hi> a Refuge for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient and Runagate, where they may ſhelter themſelves under <hi>doubtful Texts,</hi> grow obſtinate in their <hi>own Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> and revile the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Catholick Church:</hi> It is reported that there was once held a <hi>Conſult</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> whether they ſhould expunge
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:32405:90"/>all St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the noted Mint of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating Doctrines;</hi> nay, they account the whole Body of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> the moſt <hi>pernitious Engines</hi> that men could ever have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with: and he who ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſiders thoſe <hi>Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>Invectives</hi> which they have caſt upon thoſe <hi>Sacred Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns</hi> will be apt to believe that ſome of them at leaſt are ſcarce agreed among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whether their Original
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:32405:91"/>was from <hi>Heaven</hi> or from <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Provocations, what Warrants are ſuch hints as theſe to a <hi>vitious Age?</hi> What confidence and ſecurity will the <hi>Anti-Scripturiſt</hi> aſſume, when he ſhall reflect how thoſe who pretend to have had the ſole <hi>Cuſtody</hi> of the <hi>Scripture-Canon,</hi> and to have been the great <hi>Guardians</hi> of <hi>Revelation</hi> ever ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, ſhall be found to <hi>ſlight, Contemn,</hi> and <hi>Blaſpheme</hi>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:32405:91"/>thoſe reverend Truths? what havock of <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> muſt that <hi>Man</hi> make in whom <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin</hi> ſhall chance to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and made, <hi>bold</hi> by <hi>Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Cuſtom, Habit,</hi> and the <hi>applauſe</hi> of <hi>Vice;</hi> be made pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful and Eloquent by the advantages of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Parts;</hi> and eſpecially when he ſhall have his <hi>Argument</hi> recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to him by the <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Merits</hi> of a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> by the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Romans</hi> See!</p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:32405:92"/>
            <p>If we now look back and take a Survey of thoſe <hi>Ruines</hi> which I have only <hi>pointed</hi> at, what a Landskip of <hi>Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> will the <hi>Intellectual World</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? ſuch a <hi>Confuſion,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Chaos</hi> as nothing but an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Wiſdom</hi> can bring it to the beauty of <hi>Order</hi> again, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a <hi>Civil Creation</hi> can re-eſtabliſh it: and altho we cannot but acknowledg it a <hi>just Judgment</hi> of God upon us, yet I hope I have demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted how the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have been
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:32405:92"/>the <hi>immediate Executioners;</hi> as the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf is ſaid to be ſubſervient to the ends of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> in thoſe very <hi>Actions</hi> wherein he intends nothing but his <hi>own Malice;</hi> and if ever we hope to ſettle the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the <hi>Intellectual World</hi> amongſt us, we muſt with true <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Zeal,</hi> with <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> renounce all manner of <hi>Popery,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which is openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in their known and <hi>Common Doctrines,</hi> but alſo that
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:32405:93"/>which is ſecretly diſguiz'd in <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Factions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet let this <hi>diſmal Survey</hi> which I have now given be no objection to the goodneſs of God and the Promiſes of Chriſt, for ſuffering the little <hi>Remnant</hi> of his <hi>Religion</hi> to be almoſt devoured and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by the Tyranny and Craft of <hi>Anti-Christ:</hi> whilſt by the <hi>Coutroverſies</hi> of the Church our Saviour only exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the <hi>ſoundneſs</hi> of our Faith, and by the <hi>Afflictions</hi>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:32405:93"/>of it the <hi>Sincerity</hi> of our <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For God be praiſed we have ſtill ſome amongſt us who can, and dare aſſert the juſt Prerogative of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and maintain its ample ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to Religion, both to make void the neceſſity of an <hi>Infallible Chair,</hi> and to curb the extravagancies of <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm:</hi> the <hi>Clamors</hi> and <hi>Noiſes</hi> of <hi>Sceptical men,</hi> have only taught their <hi>Reaſon</hi> its <hi>ſureſt guard,</hi> brought it out of its
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:32405:94"/>
               <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> and awakened it into a <hi>fuller Orb</hi> of Evidence.</p>
            <p>Alſo the pure and immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Rules of <hi>Moral Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> ſtill ſhine in our <hi>practical Divinity;</hi> where the Precepts of Chriſt are faithfully inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted to their <hi>utmoſt Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and their utmoſt perfection is made our Rule and <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Government</hi> has its peculiar Royalty in the Doctrines <hi>our Church,</hi> it has a <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> in other Places, but a <hi>true Empire</hi> here, in our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions</hi>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:32405:94"/>tho not in our Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, Religion and Loyalty go hand in hand, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Peace embrace each other. Here the <hi>true Church</hi> of Chriſt is our <hi>Establiſhed Center,</hi> and Oh that the <hi>Civil Power</hi> were its <hi>just Circle</hi> of <hi>Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here laſtly <hi>Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> enjoys its full Splendor and Reverence, in its <hi>tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Form,</hi> 'tis a <hi>Pillar</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> a <hi>Cloud</hi> without any <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> the <hi>Immediate Preſence</hi> of the Lord
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:32405:95"/>both to <hi>conduct</hi> us, and <hi>ſecure</hi> us <hi>Victory;</hi> by <hi>this</hi> alone we can hope to withſtand the <hi>Fury</hi> of the <hi>Nations,</hi> the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>Plots</hi> of <hi>Papists.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:95"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and ſold by <hi>Wil. Cadman,</hi> at the <hi>Popes</hi> Head, in the lower walk of the New-Exchange in the <hi>Strand.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AN Inſtitution of General Hiſtory or the hiſtory of the World, by <hi>Wil. Howel, L L. D.</hi> in two Volumns.</p>
            <p>Hiſtorical Collections, or an exact Account of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the four laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of famous Memory.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:96"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharamond,</hi> a Romance compleat, in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clelia,</hi> a Romance, in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Partheniſſa,</hi> a Romance, in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Hiſtorical, Heroick Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em on the Life of the right Honourable <hi>Thomas,</hi> Earl of <hi>Oſſery,</hi> (with his Picture neatly engraven on a Copper plate) written by <hi>Elkana Settle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Hiſtorical Relation of the firſt Diſcovery of the Iſle of <hi>Madera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Proteſtant Religion is a ſure Foundation, &amp;c. by the
<pb facs="tcp:32405:96"/>Right honourable, <hi>Charles,</hi> Earl of <hi>Denby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Jeſuits Policy to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Monarchy, by a Perſon of Honour.</p>
            <p>A Warning-piece for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly in two Viſitation Sermons, at <hi>Preſton,</hi> by <hi>Seth Buſhel, D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great efficacy and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of good example, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Clergy, in a Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation Sermon at <hi>Guilford</hi> by <hi>Tho Duncomb,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the King, by <hi>Miles Barns,</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in Ordinary to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Aſſizes at <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> by <hi>Henry Pigott,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:97"/>
            <p>Two Diſcourſes: the firſt ſhewing how the chief Crite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions of Philoſophical Truth, invented by ſpeculative men, more eminently ſerve Divine Revelation, than either Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy or Natural Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The Second, manifeſting how all the Foundations of the Intellectual World, <hi>viz. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Morality, Civil Government,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> have been under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by Popiſh Doctrines and Policies.</p>
            <p>The Temple of Death with other Poems by a Perſon of Honour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32405:97"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
